A Guide to the Virginia Office of the Second Auditor - Transfer books for the Board of Public Works, 1824-1884
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia. Office of the Second Auditor. Transfer books for the Board of Public Works, 1824-1884
The Library of Virginia
SAI 74
5.4 cu. ft. (54 volumes)
Virginia. Office of the Second Auditor.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transfer information unknown.
Biographical Information
The history of the second auditor's office began in 1823 when the office was created by the General Assembly as part of an act to improve the navigation of the James and Kanawha rivers. Under the act, the second auditor was given responsibility for the Fund for Internal Improvements and for acting as secretary to the Board of Public Works. He was also appointed clerk and accountant to the directors of the Literary Fund. An act passed in 1829 made him the superintendent of the fund, and he assumed the responsibilities formerly held by the president and directors. In 1835 an act authorized the commissioners of the newly created Sinking Fund to redeem the state's debt, and the second auditor was appointed a commissioner with the responsibility, together with the state treasurer, for keeping the accounts of this fund.
Prior to the Civil War, the duties of the second auditor were fairly simple and straightforward, as were the duties of the treasurer. After the war, however, the devastation of the state's economy resulted in the creation of more numerous and complicated records concerning the redemption of the state debt. The office of the second auditor suffered from inadequate procedures for maintaining accurate records on the state's finances. By 1874, neither office had a complete or accurate account of the public debt, and between 1874 and 1877 major scandals were disclosed involving both offices and that of the sergeant at arms of the House of Delegates. Although a complete revision of the accounting methods used by both financial offices, especially the second auditor's, was called for, only minor changes were made.
In 1906 a legislative committee made periodic inspections of the finance offices. Finding that the situation in the second auditor's office remained almost as chaotic as it had been in 1874, the committee recommended that the office be abolished and its duties taken over by the first auditor. Although the committee's recommendations were not followed, its members continued to call for reform. Action was taken only after the election of Governor Harry F. Byrd, Sr., in 1926. Byrd hired a group of consultants from New York to study the finance offices, and the resulting report brought about a complete reorganization of state government in 1928. The offices of first and second auditor were abolished and replaced by a newly created office of comptroller. The second auditor's office closed its books on February 29, 1928.
Scope and Content
These records contain transfers of stocks of various internal improvement companies.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Transfer book, 1824 May 20 - 1839 September 19 (Volume 1)
- Transfer book, 1832 October 15 - 1839 January 26 (Volume 2)
- Transfer book, 1839 January 28 - September 14 (Volume 3)
- Transfer book, 1839 September 17 - 1842 February 12 (Volume 4)
- Transfer book, 1842 February 24 - 1843 June 16 (Volume 5)
- Transfer book, 1843 June 20 - 1845 December 15 (Volume 6)
- Transfer book, 1845 December 17 - 1848 March 22 (Volume 7)
- Transfer book, 1848 March 23 - 1849 May 26 (Volume 8)
- Transfer book, 1849 May 25 - 1851 January 31 (Volume 9)
- Transfer book, 1831 January 1 - 1852 September 30 (Volume 10)
- Transfer book, 1852 October 1 - 1854 January 20 (Volume 11)
- Transfer book, 1854 January 21 - 1855 January 30 (Volume 12)
- Transfer book, 1855 January 30 - December 12 (Volume 13)
- Transfer book, 1856 January 1 - 1857 February 19 (Volume 14)
- Transfer book, 1856 May 3 - 1857 September 21 (Volume 15)
- Transfer book, 1857 February 21 - November 4 (Volume 16)
- Transfer book, 1857 September 24 - 1862 January 24 (Volume 17)
- Transfer book, 1857 November 4 - 1858 October 22 (Volume 18)
- Transfer book, 1858 May 3 - 1859 April 20 (Volume 19)
- Transfer book, 1859 February 11 - March 14 (Volume 20)
- Transfer book, 1860 March 14 - 1861 March 20 (Volume 21)
- Transfer book, 1861 March 21 - 1862 May 14 (Volume 22)
- Transfer book, 1862 August 9 - 1863 May 30 (Volume 23)
- Transfer book, 1863 June 1 - 1865 April 1 (Volume 24)
- Transfer book, 1865 July 11 - 1866 August 29 (Volume 25)
- Transfer book, 1866 April 27 - July 19 (Volume 26)
- Transfer book, 1866 August 30 - 1867 May 21 (Volume 27)
- Transfer book, 1866 October 1 - 1868 January 23 (Volume 28)
- Transfer book, 1867 January 1 - 1868 March 20 (Volume 29)
- Transfer book, 1867 April 27 - 1869 June 9 (Volume 30)
- Transfer book, 1867 June 8 - 1868 June 29 (Volume 31)
- Transfer book, 1868 May 4 - November 24 (Volume 32)
- Transfer book, 1868 November 24 - 1869 August 20 (Volume 33)
- Transfer book, 1869 April 7 - 1870 June 29 (Volume 34)
- Transfer book, 1869 October 2 - 1870 April 9 (Volume 35)
- Transfer book, 1870 July 1 - December 9 (Volume 36)
- Transfer book, 1871 January 3 - June 9 (Volume 37)
- Transfer book, 1871 May 1 - 1880 April 19 (Volume 38)
- Transfer book, 1871 July 15 - 1872 March 9 (Volume 39)
- Transfer book, 1871 July 15 - 1872 March 16 (Volume 40)
- Transfer book, 1871 November 7 - 1881 November 30 (Volume 41)
- Transfer book, 1871 December 9 - 1872 September 3 (Volume 42)
- Transfer book, 1872 March 11 - 1873 April 9 (Volume 43)
- Transfer book, 1872 September 6 - 1873 April 8 (Volume 44)
- Transfer book, 1873 April 8 - 1874 February 28 (Volume 45)
- Transfer book, 1873 May 1 - 1874 January 25 (Volume 46)
- Transfer book, 1874 March 2 - November 3 (Volume 47)
- Transfer book, 1874 November 3 - 1875 September 17 (Volume 48)
- Transfer book, 1875 April 10 - 1878 August 8 (Volume 49)
- Transfer book, 1875 September 17 - 1876 September 28 (Volume 50)
- Transfer book, 1876 September 28 - 1878 November 29 (Volume 51)
- Transfer book, 1878 August 10 - 1921 January 12 (Volume 52)
- Transfer book, 1878 November 29 - 1880 December 9 (Volume 53)
- Transfer book, 1881 December 1 - 1884 May 2 (Volume 54)